## Research Interests

I am deeply interested in studying social cognition. My main research motivations are understanding the cognitive basis of how people understand other's mental state (i.e., theory of mind), and how individuals coordinate to each other. By using a range of experimental and individual differences analytic tools, I explore how people reach common judgments with complete strangers without any form of communication at all (i.e., pure coordination games). These games are useful empirical platforms for understanding how people use contents in social interaction.

## **Education and Qualifications**

- 2019-now PhD. in Psychology, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom
  - 2018 Certificate in Teaching at Higher Education, University of Atacama, Chile
- 2013–2015 MPhil. Cognitive Psychology, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Australia
- 2010-2012 Msc. Applied Social Sciences, University of Tarapacá, Chile
- 2004–2009 Bsc. Psychology, University of Tarapacá, Chile

#### Featured Publications

- 1. Wilson, R., Hruby, A., **Perez-Zapata, D.**, van der Kleij, S.W., & Apperly, I. (2022). Is Recursive "Mindreading" Really an Exception to Limitations on Recursive Thinking. *Journal of Experimental Psychology: General.*
- 2. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Cuadra-Martínez, D., Valenzuela-Barros, C., & Salgado-García, P. (2019). Theory of mind and its relationship with behavioural inhibition in Chilean preschools. *Studies in Psychology, 40* (2), 443-463.
- 3. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Slaughter, V., & Henry, J. (2016). Cultural effects in Mindreading. *Cognition, 146*, 410-414.
- 4. Slaughter, V., & **Perez-Zapata, D.**. (2014). Cultural variations in the development of mind reading. *Child Development Perspectives*, 8 (4), 237-241.

#### **Preprints**

- Perez-Zapata, D.., & Apperly, I. (2022, October 11). An International Study of Pure Coordination Games: Adaptable Solutions When Intuitions are Presumed to Vary. https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/8fqwn, PsyArXiv.
- 2. **Perez-Zapata, D.**., McKenzie-Smart, X., Charest, I., & Apperly, I. (2021, July 3). Meeting and Missing Minds: Children and Adults Use Alignment of Intuitions to Solve Pure Coordination Games. https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/96hbp, *PsyArXiv*.

# Grants, Awards and Scholarships

2022–2024 Regular Fondecyt (Chilean Research Grant) №1220664, Title: "The Role of Heuristic and Deliberative Information Processing, Receptivity, Naive Skepticism, and Information Susceptibility in the Health System."

Co-investigator: **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Principal Investigator: Dr. Rodrigo Ferrer Urbina, School of Psychology, University of Tarapacá. Other Co-investigators: Dr. Marcos Carmona Halty (University of Tarapacá), Dr. Hermán Elgueta (University of Magallanes) y Dr. Guillermo Puebla (University of Bristol, UK).

2019–2021 Regular Fondecyt (Chilean Research Grant) Nº1190006, Title: "A Descriptive Model for Causal Classification"

Co-investigator: **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Principal Investigator: Dr. Sergio Chaigneau, CSCN, School of Psychology, Adolfo Ibáñez University . Other Co-investigators: Dr. Enrique Canessa (Adolfo Ibáñez University ) and Dr. Guillermo Puebla (University of Bristol, UK).

- 2022 LES PGR Travel Award Scheme, University of Birmingham, UK
- 2021 PhD Grindley Grant Experimental Psychology Society, UK.
- 2021 Internal pump prime funding School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, UK.
- 2019-2023 ANID Scholarship for Overseas PhD Programs (Government of Chile Scholarship)
- 2013-2015 ANID Scholarship for Overseas MPhil Programs (Government of Chile Scholarship)
  - 2009 Early Career Research Grant for Undergraduates, University of Tarapaca, Chile.
- 2005-2009 President of the Republic Scholarship for Undergraduates (Government of Chile Scholarship)

# Relevant Teaching Experience

- 2020-2022 **Teaching Assistant**, *University of Birmingham*, United Kingdom
  - (1) Social and Cognitive Development, (2) Introduction to Programming in R & Python, (3) Introduction to Social and Differential Psychology (4) Research Methods C, Neuroscience Methods 1, (5) and Language and Communication Modules.
- 2016–2019 Lecturer, School of Psychology, University of Atacama, Copiapó, Chile
  I taught a number of modules at Bachelor and Master levels. (1) General Psychology, (2) Cognitive Psychology, (3) Introduction to Neuropsychology, (4) Developmental Psychology, (5) Quantitative Methods, (6) Introduction to Cognitive Neuroscience among others.
- 2015–2016, Teaching Fellow, University of Tarapacá & Santo Tomás University, Arica, Chile
- 2010–2012 (1) Developmental Psychology, (2) Social Psychology, (3) Introduction to Cognitive Neuroscience, (4) Introduction to Psychology, (5) Learning Psychology, and (6) Social Research.
- 2014–2015 **Tutor**, *The University of Queensland*, Brisbane, Australia *Introduction to Cognitive and Physiological Psychology*.

#### Research Skills

- Statistics SPSS, Python and R Programming Languages. I use both programming languages at a research proficient level by applying a range of packages/libraries in the multiple stages of the data analysis process such as data pre-processing, descriptive data processing, data visualisation, and inferential data processing.
- Experimental E-Prime, OpenSesame, Qualtrics. I have used this set of experimental software across different stages of my research work for conducting a number of experimental (e.g., E-Prime, OpenSesame, Qualtrics) and individual differences studies (e.g., Qualtrics).

Crowdsourcing Prolific, Cloud Research. I have successfully recruited participants from the UK (Prolific) Platforms and from many countries of the world (Cloud Research) using both platforms. Options available in both tools allow to collect and end up with reliable quality data.

Open Science OSF, PsyArXiv. To promote scientific reproducibility and research transparency, I upload a variety of research outputs (e.g., datasets, data analysis code, supplementary materials, presentations, etc.) on my OSF profiles (link: https://osf.io/dpxb7/), and post my research reports first on PsyArXiv, before submitting my papers to peer-reviewed journals.

#### Profesional Service

Ad Hoc Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology Reviewer International Journal of Neuroscience Plos One Revista de Psicología, University of Chile

### Full List of Publications

- 1. Wilson, R., Hruby, A., Perez-Zapata, D., van der Kleij, S.W., & Apperly, I. (2022). Is Recursive "Mindreading" Really an Exception to Limitations on Recursive Thinking. Journal of Experimental Psychology: General.
- 2. Cuadra-Martínez, D., Perez-Zapata, D., Sandoval-Díaz, J., Rubio, J. (2022) Clima Escolar y Factores Asociados: Modelo Predictivo de Ecuaciones Estructurales. Revista de Psicología PUCP, 40(2),685-709. https://doi.org/10.18800/psico.202202.002
- J., Cuadra-Martínez, & Perez-Zapata. Del 3. Sandoval-Díaz, **D.** (2022). afrontamiento colectivo al crecimiento postraumático comunitario: análisis mediacional del empoderamiento ante un desastre climatológico. Revista *Psykhe*,31(2).https://doi.org/10.7764/psykhe.2019.22345
- 4. Cuadra-Martínez, D., Castro-Carrasco, P., Tognetta, L., Perez-Zapata, D., Veliz, D., & Menares, N. (2021). Teorías subjetivas de la convivencia escolar: ¿Qué dicen los padres? Revista Psicologia Escolar e Educacional, 25, 1-9.
- 5. Cuadra-Martínez, Castro-Carrasco, P., Oyanedel, C., González, I., Sandoval-Díaz, J., & Perez-Zapata, D. (2021). Formación de la Identidad Profesional frente a la Crisis Global Socioambiental. Liberabit, 27 (2), 1-16. DOI:10.24265/liberabit.2021.v27n2.05
- 6. Cuadra-Martínez, D., Castro-Carrasco, P., Sandoval-Díaz, J., Perez-Zapata, D., Mora-Dabancens, D. (2020). COVID-19 y comportamiento psicológico: revisión sistemática de los efectos psicológicos de las pandemias del siglo XXI. Revista Medica de Chile, 148(8), 1193-1208.
- 7. Perez-Zapata, D., Cuadra-Martínez, D., Valenzuela-Barros, C., & Salgado-García, P. (2019). Theory of mind and its relationship with behavioural inhibition in Chilean preschools/Teoría de la mente y su relación con inhibición conductual en pre-escolares chilenos. Studies in Psychology, 40 (2), 443-463.
- 8. Cuadra-Martínez, D., Sandoval-Díaz, J., Perez-Zapata, D., Castro-Carrasco, P., Véliz-Vergara, D., Guzman-Ávalos, J., & Ramos-Thompson, G. (2019). Helping One's Neighbor: Teaching and Learning Prosocial Behavior in a Religious Community. Religions, 10 (9), 515; https://doi.org/10.3390/rel10090515

- Cuadra-Martínez, D., Perez-Zapata, D., Sandoval-Díaz, J., Valdivia-Díaz, J., Palma-Flores, C., & Mora-Dabancens, D. (2019). Predictores de identidad profesional en estudiantes de psicología: un estudio de análisis de senderos. Actualidades en Psicología, 33(127), 1-17.
- Sandoval-Díaz, J., & Perez-Zapata, D. (2017). Concepción de aprendizaje en estudiantes universitarios de la carrera de psicología del extremo norte de Chile. Universitas Psychologica, 16 (2), 1-11.
- 11. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Slaughter, V., & Henry, J. (2016). Cultural effects in Mindreading. *Cognition*, *146*, 410-414.
- 12. Slaughter, V., & **Perez-Zapata**, **D.** (2014). Cultural variations in the development of mind reading. *Child Development Perspectives*, 8 (4), 237-241.
- Perez-Zapata, D., Peralta-Montecinos, J., & Fernández-Dávila, P. (2014). Influencia de variables organizacionales en la calidad de vida laboral de funcionarios del sector público de salud en el extremo norte de Chile. *Universitas Psychologica*, 13 (2), 541-551.
- 14. **Perez-Zapata, D.**,& Zurita, R. (2014). Calidad de vida laboral en trabajadores de salud pública en Chile. *Salud y Sociedad, 5* (2), 172-180.
- 15. Romero, J., C., & **Perez-Zapata, D.** (2010). Craving, experiencia, conciencia y temporalidad en adicciones. Una reflexión clínica desde la fenomenología de Husserl, enfoque de Varela y la biología de la cognición de Maturana. *Límite*, 5(21), 95-116.

#### Full List of Presentations

- 1. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, McKenzie-Smart, X., Charest, I., & Apperly, I. (2022). "Children and Adults Solve Pure Coordination Games Via Alignment of Intuitions", Cognitive Artificial Intelligence Meeting at Royal Society, September 2022, London, UK
- 2. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, & Apperly, I. (2022). "An International Study of Pure Coordination Games: Adaptable Solutions When Intuitions are Presumed to Vary.", Intuitive Alignment Workshop, April 2022, Birmingham, UK
- 3. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, McKenzie-Smart, X., Charest, I., & Apperly, I. (2022). "Alineamiento Intuitivo y Cognición Social: ¿Cómo Niños y Adultos Resuelven Juegos Puros de Coordinación?", VIII Congreso Regional de la Sociedad Interamericana de la Psicologia, Julio 2022, Concepcion, Chile
- 4. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, & Apperly, I. (2022). "Alineamiento Intuitivo: Nuestros Juicios Intuitivos Varían de acuerdo con Quien nos Estemos Coordinando", VIII Congreso Regional de la Sociedad Interamericana de la Psicologia, Julio 2022, Concepcion, Chile
- Cuadra-Martínez, D., Castro-Carrasco, P., González-Palta, I., Oyanedel, C., Sandoval-Diaz, J., Perez-Zapata, D., & (2022). "Preservice Teacher Professional Identity: Influence of the Teacher Educator and the Teacher Education Model", The 10th European Conference on Education (ECE2022), July 2022, London, United Kingdom
- Perez-Zapata, D., McKenzie-Smart, X., Charest, I., & Apperly, I. (2022). "Children and Adults Solve Pure Coordination Games Via Alignment of Intuitions", Conferencia de la "Association for Psychological Science" (APS), Mayo 2022, Chicago, Estados Unidos
- 7. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, McKenzie-Smart, X., Charest, I., & Apperly, I. (2022). "Children and Adults Solve Pure Coordination Games Using Alignment of Intuitions", 12th annual Budapest CEU Conference on Cognitive Development, Enero 2022, Budapest, Hungry

- 8. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, McKenzie-Smart, X., Charest, I., & Apperly, I. (2021). "El Uso del Alineamiento Intuitivo en Niños y Adultos para Resolver Juegos Puros de Coordinación", XV Congreso Chileno de Psicología, Santiago, Chile.
- 9. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, McKenzie-Smart, X., Charest, I., & Apperly, I. (2021). "El Uso del Alineamiento Intuitivo en Niños y Adultos para Resolver Juegos Puros de Coordinación", "Primer Encuentro de Estudiantes de Doctorado en Psicología y Ciencias Afines", Modalidad Online, organizado por la Universidad de Concepcion, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile y Universidad de La Frontera, Chile.
- 10. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, McKenzie-Smart, X., Charest, I., & Apperly, I. (2021, July). Meeting and Missing Minds: Children and Adults Use Alignment of Intuitions to Solve Pure Coordination Games, Online Experimental Psychology Society (EPS) Conference, United Kingdom.
- 11. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Cuadra-Martínez, D., & Valenzuela-Barrios, C. (2018). Comprendiendo la relación entre la Escala de Teoría de la Mente y funciones ejecutivas en niños chilenos, XIII Congreso Chileno de Psicología, Chile, Temuco
- 12. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Sandoval, J., & Cuadra-Martínez, D. (2017). Schadenfreude y Autoeficacia en estudiantes universitarios: disfrutando el traspié de los demás., XII Congreso Chileno de Psicología, Chile, La Serena
- 13. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Slaughter, V., y Henry, J. (2015). Efectos culturales en teoría de mente. Presentación en "X Congreso Nacional de Psicología", Universidad de Talca, Talca, Chile.
- 14. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Slaughter, V., y Henry, J. (2015). Cultural targets affect adult mindreading reasoning. Presentación en "The Origins and Transmission of Culture; an interdisciplinary approach", University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom
- 15. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Slaughter, V., y Henry, J. (2014). Intracultural effects on adult theory-of-mind reasoning. Presentación en "12th International Conference on Cognitive Neuroscience", Brisbane, Australia.
- 16. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, y Zurita, R. (2014). Percepción de calidad de vida laboral en funcionarios públicos de salud, IX Congreso Nacional de Psicología, Chillán, Chile.
- 17. Zurita, R., & **Perez-Zapata, D.** (2014). Calidad de Vida Laboral y Satisfacción Laboral en organizaciones de salud pública y privada, IX Congreso Nacional de Psicología, Chillán, Chile.
- 18. Puebla, R., & **Perez-Zapata, D.** (2010). Razonamiento causal y conceptos, V Congreso Nacional de Psicología, Arica, Chile.
- 19. **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Puebla, G., & Sandoval, J. (2009). Conceptos y categorización en niños. IV Congreso Nacional de Psicología, Temuco, Chile.

# Public Engagement and Science Dissemination

1 **Perez-Zapata, D.**, Slaughter, V., & Henry, J. (2015).¿Influye la cultura sobre la capacidad de entender lo que piensan los demás? Un estudio de Teoría de la Mente con muestras australianas y chilenas. *Ciencia Cognitiva* 

#### **Profesional Affiliations**

2021-now Experimental Psychology Society member, United Kingdom.

2022-now Association for Psychological Science member, United States.

# Referees

Prof. Ian Apperly, i.a.apperly@bham.ac.uk, University of Birmingham, UK.

Prof. Virginia Slaughter, vps@psy.uq.edu.au, The University of Queensland, Australia.

Prof. Julie Henry, julie.henry@uq.edu.au, The University of Queensland, Australia.

Dr. Ian Charest, ian. charest. 1@umontreal.ca, University of Montreal, Canada.

CV Updated: 26.10.2022.